<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Article Review on Graham Tierney</title>
    <link>/categories/article-review/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Article Review on Graham Tierney</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/article-review/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Reviews: The Book of Why and Bad Blood</title>
      <link>/post/2018_10_books/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018_10_books/</guid>
      <description>Judea Pearle’s The Book of Why: The New Science of Cause and Effect I was honestly surprised by how much I liked this book. It covers Pearle’s new work on causal diagrams, directed graphs were each node represents a variable and edges point in the direction of the causal effect. His claim is that these graphs make previously “squishy” arguments about identification mathematically robust, simplify many hard-to-explain causal concepts, and will be useful in building strong artificial intelligence because the graphs are machine-readable, unlike other causal identifying assumptions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Science in Mental Health</title>
      <link>/post/2018_09_mental_health/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018_09_mental_health/</guid>
      <description>I came across two articles recently that I thought spoke to each other in an interesting way. The first was a New York Times piece about the failings of data science firms who try to identify school shootings before they happen by social media posts. The second was a Vox article about how a crisis counseling hotline successfully used data science to flag callers who are at higher risk of suicide or self-harm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Article Round Up June 2018: Income Inequality, Partisan Economies, and Trump Tweets to Hate Crimes</title>
      <link>/post/2018_06_best_reads/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018_06_best_reads/</guid>
      <description>This is my second article round up. The first is over at my old blog here. In this post, I’ll briefly cover two Atlantic articles related to economic inequality and the differing economic expectations of democrats and republicans. Most time is spent reviewing a new working paper on the correlation between Trump’s twitter activity and hate crimes, and thinking about how it could make the jump from correlation to causation.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>